New England Steam Gauge Company Records
© 2005 University of Connecticut
New England Steam Gauge Company Records.
undated, 1912-1961.
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center.
New England Steam Gauge Company.
3.25 linear feet.
MSS19800030
The Technical Equipment Company (TEC) had its general headquarters in New York City and a manufacturing plant in Niantic, Connecticut, by 1913. In the spring of 1913, TEC took over the gauge department of Utica Steam Gauge Company and the Libby Valve and Packing Company. By 1914, the company had become the New England Steam Gauge Company and had its base in Niantic.
History
The Technical Equipment Company (TEC) had its general headquarters in New York City and a manufacturing plant in Niantic, Connecticut, by 1913. In the spring of 1913, TEC took over the gauge department of Utica Steam Gauge Company and the Libby Valve and Packing Company. By 1914, the company had become the New England Steam Gauge Company and had its base in Niantic. There are no company records in the collection dated after the early 1950s, although the will of George H. Clarke includes valuable company stock in 1961.
Scope and Content
The collection consists of the business records of the New England Steam Gauge Company and its predecessors. The original collection contained approximately 20 linear feet but was heavily weeded when acquired. Materials in the collection include correspondence, invoices, purchase orders, tax and financial records and suppliers' catalogues, all of which illustrate the role the company played in designing, manufacturing and supplying gauges for railroads, industry, university studies and individuals. Companies represented in the collection include American Brass Company, M.G. Melvin Company, Phospher Bronze Smelting Company, General Fire Extinguisher Company, New York, New Haven and Hartford Railroad, Taylor Instruments Company, Pennsylvania Lines, Pennsylvania Railroad Company, and C.J. Tagliabue Manufacturing Company.
Related Material
Archives & Special Collections has a substantial collection of Connecticut business records. For detailed information on these collections please contact the curator or ask at the reference desk.
Index Terms
This record series is indexed under the following controlled access subject terms.
Subjects:
Steam-engines.; Railroad gauges.; Pressure vessels—Valves.; Pressure gauges.; Connecticut—Business, industries, and trades.; Niantic (Conn.)—Business, industries, and trades.
Document Types:
Correspondence.; Publications.; Blueprints.; Administrative Records.; Financial Records.
Occupations:
Manufacturer of gauges.
Restrictions on Access
There are no access restrictions on this collection.
Acquisition Information
Unknown.
Detailed Description
- Series I: Records, undated, 1912-1961
  - Correspondence, undated, 1912-1952
    - No date (Box 1:, Folder 1)
    - 1912 October - December (Box 1:, Folder 2)
    - 1913 January - March (Box 1:, Folder 3)
    - 1913 April - June (Box 1:, Folder 4)
    - 1913 July - September (Box 1:, Folder 5)
    - 1913 October - November (Box 1:, Folder 6)
    - 1914 (Box 1:, Folder 7)
    - 1915 (Box 1:, Folder 8)
    - 1916 (Box 1:, Folder 9)
    - 1917 (Box 1:, Folder 10)
    - 1918 (Box 1:, Folder 11)
    - 1919 (Box 1:, Folder 12)
    - 1920 (Box 1:, Folder 13)
    - 1921 (Box 1:, Folder 14)
    - 1922 (Box 1:, Folder 15)
    - 1923 (Box 2:, Folder 16)
    - 1924 (Box 2:, Folder 17)
    - 1925 (Box 2:, Folder 18)
    - 1926 (Box 2:, Folder 19)
    - 1927 (Box 2:, Folder 20)
    - 1928 (Box 2:, Folder 21)
    - 1929-1931 (Box 2:, Folder 22)
    - 1932-1939 (Box 2:, Folder 23)
    - 1940-1941 (Box 2:, Folder 24)
    - 1942-1945 (Box 2:, Folder 25)
    - 1946-1949 (Box 2:, Folder 26)
    - 1950-1952 (Box 2:, Folder 27)
  - Financial Records, undated, 1917-1941
    - Company statement, 1917 (Box 2:, Folder 28)
    - Day Book, 1920-1923 (Box 2:, Folder 29)
    - Factory Expense reports, undated, 1915-1921 (Box 2:, Folder 30)
    - Income Tax records, 1916-1918 (Box 3:, Folder 31)
    - Journal, 1930-1941 (Box 3:, Folder 32)
    - Record book, 1930-1939 (Box 3:, Folder 33)
    - Unidentified, undated, 1915-1916 (Box 3:, Folder 34)
  - Legal files, 1917-1961 (Box 3:, Folder 35)
  - Industry brochures, pamphlets and publications, undated (Box 3:, Folder 36)
  - Product Blueprints, 1922-1959 (Box 3:, Folder 37)
  - Product Blueprints, 1948-1959 (Othertype OS:, Folder 38)